<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<recipe name="Shrewsberry Cakes">
    <title>Shrewsberry Cakes</title>
<!--XML COMMENT FROM DR. B! The @ symbol is something we use to mention an attribute.
    So I could comment on the use of @xml:id in this file. And about @pointer, and how we use
    # marks ("hash marks" or "octothorpes" b/c they have 8 points).
    -->
    <about><label>About this recipe</label> Healthiness : (235 votes) <difficulty>Difficulty: 2 out
            of 5 difficulty</difficulty> View a modern version of this recipe
            <para>Shrewsberry/Shrewsbury cakes are a kind of biscuit. They are less crumbly than a
            shortbread but have a buttery flavour. Sweet foods like biscuits were popular with the
            Georgians and were easier to make because of the the increased importing of sugar from
            the sugar plantations in the Caribbean. They were made to accompany many dishes but were
            popular with syllabub, which is a sugared, whipped cream, flavoured with cider or
            sherry. Sugar was an important trade item and refined (white) sugar was very
            fashionable.</para>
        <para>This recipe uses white sugar, which would have been pinched off a sugarloaf and then
            ground (beaten) until fine enough to use in the recipe.</para>
        <para>Traditionally they are baked as thick, large biscuits and were able to be kept for
            long periods of time. </para>
        <para>This recipe comes from <title>A delightful Daily Exercise for Ladies and Gentlewomen</title> </para>
        <blockQuote>"Take a quart of very fine flouwer, eight onces of fine sugar beaten and cersed,
            twelve ounces sweet butter, nutmeg grated, damaske rosewater- work together with your
            hands for halfe an houre, then roule in little round cakes about the thickness of three
            shillings, then take a glasse and cut the cakes, then strow some flower on white papers
            and bake them in an oven as hotte as for manchet. If the oven be not hotte sett your lid
            downe ( there is a long explanantion for testing/changing the heat in the period oven
            which i have omitted) until they be baked enough, for they must lokke browne not white.
            you may keep them halfe a yeare but new baked are best."</blockQuote>
        <para>For images of the cooking process see our Shrewsbury Cakes Pictures.</para>
    </about>

    <credits>With thanks to <name who="IP">Ian Pycroft</name> of Black Knight Historical and to The
        Georgian House, Bristol.</credits>

    <list type="ingredients">
        <label>Ingredients</label>
        <item type="grain" quant="4" unit="oz" xml:id="wflour">4oz plain white flour</item>
        <item type="sweetener" quant="4" unit="oz" xml:id="cstrSugar">4oz white, caster sugar</item>
        <item type="fat" quant="4" unit="oz" xml:id="sltdButter">4oz salted butter (very soft, works
            best)</item>
        <item type="spice" quant=".25" unit="#tsp" xml:id="nutmeg">1/4 teaspoon of grated (or
            ground) nutmeg</item>
        <item type="liquid" range="2 3" unit="#tsp" xml:id="rosewater">2-3 teaspoon rosewater</item>
        <item type="liquid" range="3 5" unit="#tbsp" xml:id="tapWater">3-5 tablespoons tapwater (at
            room temperature)</item>
        <item type="sweetener">optional: a little caster sugar to sprinkle on the top</item>
        <note>( Note: You may need more water to make a stiff dough, it will depend on the flour you
            use.)</note>
    </list>

    <list type="equipment">
        <label>Equipment</label>
        <item type="measurement" xml:id="scale">Weighing scales</item>
        <item type="measurement" xml:id="tsp">Teaspoon</item>
        <item type="measurement" xml:id="tbsp">Tablespoon</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="grater">Grater (optional)</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="mxBowl">Mixing bowl</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="wdSpoon">Wooden spoon</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="rlgPin">Rolling pin</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="lgCutter">Large cutter</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="fork">Fork</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="bkgSheet">Baking sheet</item>
        <item type="tool" xml:id="clgRack">Cooling rack</item>
    </list>
   

    <list type="process">
        <label>Making and cooking it</label>
        <reminder>Always wash your hands before preparing food.</reminder>

        <step>Heat the oven with a good fire</step>
        <step>Put the <ingred pointer="#wflour">flour</ingred>, <ingred pointer="#cstrSugar"
                >sugar</ingred> and <ingred pointer="#sltdButter">butter</ingred> into a <equip
                pointer="#mxBowl">bowl</equip> and mix well with a <equip pointer="#fork"
            >fork</equip>. You should end up with fine breadcrumbs. If the <ingred
                pointer="#sltdButter">butter</ingred> is hard, you will need to rub it in with your
            fingertips, like making pastry</step>
        <step>Add the <ingred pointer="#rosewater">rosewater</ingred> and enough <ingred
                pointer="#tapWater">water</ingred> to make a soft dough</step>
        <step>Gather the dough together with your fingers in the <equip pointer="#mxBowl"
                >bowl</equip></step>
        <step>Kneed lightly</step>
        <step><ingred pointer="#wflour">Flour</ingred> a surface and roll the dough out to 3
            shillings depth</step>
        <step>Use a glass to cut the cakes out</step>
        <step>Prick the surface of the cakes with a <equip pointer="#fork">fork</equip></step>
        <step>Space the cakes out on <equip pointer="#bkgSheet">paper</equip> and bake until the cakes
            are golden brown</step>
        <step>Serve cold with syllabub</step>
    </list>
</recipe>
